译者注：
本书尚无中文译本，似有民间翻译，但本视频所用翻译均为个人拙译
杜格尔·狄克逊的《人后之人》
Man After Man by Dougal Dixon
可谓一部石破天惊的推测进化传奇
is a ground-breaking speculative evolution story
其故事纵横五百万年，乃至更久远的未来
that spans 5 million years and beyond.
故事始于24世纪
It's the 24th century,
彼时的地球已被污染和人口过剩糟蹋得满目疮痍
and the Earth has been utterly wrecked by pollution and overpopulation.
基于此，一小撮“天选之子”得以离开地球，踏上了殖民外星球的征程
With this, a small number of humans are chosen to leave the Earth in order to colonize other planets.
杰米兹·斯穆特便是其中一员
Jimez Smoot is one such example.
为了协助建造运载他们的宏伟太空方舟，两个后人类物种应运而生
Two post-human species are created to aid in the construction of the great spacecraft that will transport them.
它们是“水栖改造人”和“真空改造人”
The Aquamorphs and the Vacuumorphs.
前者专为水下作业而生
The former were designed to live and work under water,
后者则被设计用于在毫无空气的寂寥太空中劳作
and the latter were designed to live and work in the airless void of space.
这些亚种拥有完整的智慧，能够胜任各种繁复的使命
These subspecies were fully sapient and able to engage in complicated tasks,
但遗憾的是，他们被剥夺了繁衍后代的能力
but they were bred to be infertile.
当他们的使命完成后，这些工具人又苟活了一阵子，才最终走向灭亡
Once their work had been completed, they lived on for a while before perishing.
三百载光阴倏忽而过
300 years hence.
此时，地球开始渐渐缓过劲来，而人类也分化成了两大阵营
By this point, the Earth is beginning to recover, and two groups of humans have emerged.
一是选择了田园牧歌式的生活，保留着纯粹人类血脉的“农耕派”
Those who have adopted a more agrarian lifestyle and remain as pure humans,
而另一派，则是所谓的“高技术宅”
and the other type, the high-techs.
前者拒斥了高新科技，过着日出而作、日落而息的简朴健康生活
While the former have effectively shunned advanced technology and lived simple, healthy lives as farmers,
后者则因为近亲繁殖和对技术的过度沉迷
the latter have come about as a result of inbreeding and over-reliance on technology.
他们的身体孱弱不堪，已然退化，只能蜷缩在机械摇篮里代步
They exist in a fragile and degenerate state within mechanical cradles that they use to move around in.
真正做到了大门不出，二门不迈
They never leave their homes or go outside at all.
不过很讽刺，正是这群躯壳虽已腐朽的“高技术宅”
But they are the ones who, despite their physically weakened state,
在不断推进新人类形态的基因创造工程
move forward with the genetic creation of new human forms.
此时还出现了一群基因工程改造的“水栖人”
Also present are the genetically engineered aquatics,
他们的生活方式与那早已灭绝的水栖改造人颇为相似
beings similar in lifestyle to the now extinct aquamorphs.
这便是“高技术宅”们的开山之作
These are the first creations of the high-techs.
又过了500年，“高技术宅”们的花名册上又添了四大新物种
500 years hence, there are now four additional species created by the high-techs,
每一种都是为了适应天差地别的环境而量身打造
each one designed to live in vastly different environments.
“苔原行者”诞生于寒冷的冰雪之地
The tundra-dwellers were made to live in the colder, snowy regions.
“平原行者”，栖息在干旱之地的茵茵草原
The plains-dwellers, who live on the grassy plains of arid lands,
填补了曾经属于羚羊、角马和水牛的生态位
filling the niche left behind by gazelles, wildebeest, and water buffalo.
“森林行者”，顾名思义，生活在丛林密布的地区
The forest-dweller, of course, lives in forested areas,
扮演着过去由猿、猩猩和树懒担当的角色
filling the roles previously occupied by apes, orangutans, and sloths.
而“温带林行者”则接管了鹿、熊和狼等动物的职责
And the temperate woodland-dweller fills the role of creatures like deer, bears, and wolves.
随着这五大物种被播撒到地球各地，人类演化的新航程正式启碇
With these five species having been seeded throughout the Earth, humanity's new course can begin.
千年弹指一挥间，“高技术宅”们自身也发生了翻天覆地的变化
1,000 years hence, the high-tech have themselves changed a great deal.
他们总算甩掉了在“古代”赖以维生的机械摇篮和各种义体
They have managed to shed the mechanical cradles and body parts that kept them alive in ancient times.
如今他们的外壳由一坨坨的有机材料构成
Their outer shells are now comprised of blob-like organic material,
还会根据时下的流行风尚，随意增减附肢的数量
with additional limbs being added on or taken away as current fashion dictates.
五千年后
5,000 years hence.
“温带林行者”已经开始重拾他们失落的智慧
The temperate woodland-dweller has begun to recover its lost sapience.
他们现在能建造简陋的构筑物
They can now build rudimentary structures,
并且点亮了一项奇特的技能，那就是从父母那里继承记忆
and have developed the curious ability to inherit memories from their parents.
他们成了“记忆传承者”
They have become the memory people.
同一时期，还活跃着“平原行者”的后裔
Also present during this time are the descendants of the plains-dweller,
简称为“迁徙者”
called simply Migrants.
“热带树栖者”也于此刻粉墨登场
The tropical tree-dweller has also now come into being,
他们是“森林行者”的后代
itself a descendant of the forest-dweller.
不同的演化分支开始显现
The different branches are beginning to emerge.
一万年后，“苔原行者”们
10,000 years hence, the tundra-dwellers,
以及“温带林行者”的一支后裔
and a subset of the temperate woodland-dweller descendants,
似乎形成了一种共生关系
seem to have formed a symbiotic relationship.
他们分别演变成了“猎手承载者”和“猎手共生体”
They have become the hunter-carrier, and the hunter-symbiont, respectively.
他们彼此相处融洽
They each seem to be comfortable enough with each other,
亲密无间
familiar enough with each other,
到了相依为命的地步
to depend on each other for survival.
此时还出现了“冬眠者”
Also now in existence are the hibernators,
也是“温带林行者”的后裔
descendants of the temperate woodland-dwellers.
该物种的雄性会在酷寒的冬日里呼呼大睡
The males of this species hibernate during the brutally cold winter months.
“洞穴行者”，同样源自“温带林行者”
The cave-dweller, another descendant of the temperate woodland-dweller,
现在盘踞在地下的洞穴和隧道中
now populates the subterranean caves and tunnels,
只在夜间冒险爬上地表，狩猎觅食
venturing to the surface at night in order to hunt.
五万年后
50,000 years hence.
演化的脚步永不停歇
Evolution never stops,
三个新物种如今正漫步于林地与平原
and three new species are now roaming the woodlands and the plains.
“岛民”是人类的一个分支
The islander is a species of humans,
他们的身材嘛，相当娇小
rather small in stature,
居住在热带火山群岛上
who inhabit the tropical volcanic islands.
“寻水者”是一种长得酷似黑猩猩的物种
The water-seeker is a chimpanzee-like species
他们进化出了在广袤大地上侦测水源的本领
that has evolved to detect water over vast distances.
这两种生物，都脱胎于“温带林行者”
Both of these are descendants of the temperate woodland-dweller.
“群居平原行者”则是“迁徙者”的后裔
The communal plains-dweller is a descendant of the migrants,
算起来，“迁徙者”大概在四万五千年前首次登场
who first emerged around 45,000 years before.
五十万年后
500,000 years hence.
在随后的45万年里，“群居平原行者”还在持续发育
The communal plains-dweller has developed further still in the ensuing 450,000 years,
最终成了一个被称为“社交者”的物种
becoming a species known as the social.
他们的手上长出了令人生畏的骨刃，专门用于格斗
They possess formidable blades on their hands, used for combat.
“舟人”也在这时闪亮登场
The boat-person has also emerged by this point.
他们是“记忆传承者”的进化形态
These are an evolved form of the memory people,
凭借着祖传的记忆，他们学会了造船
who use their ancestral memory to build boats
而这些船的样子，和他们智人先祖的造物简直是一个模子刻出来的
that look very much like those of their Homo sapiens forebearers.
100万年后
1,000,000 years hence.
“水栖人”进化出了一种新能力，能用一层凝胶状涂层覆盖全身
The aquatics have evolved the ability to cover themselves in a gelatinous coating,
这让他们得以壮着胆子爬上干燥的陆地
which allows them to venture out onto dry land.
看来在他们的血脉深处
It would seem that there is something within them
有一种力量在驱使他们，重返其遥远祖先的陆地世界
that compels them to return to the Terranian world of their distant ancestors.
“水栖人”绝对是值得重点关注的潜力股
The aquatics are the ones to watch out for.
200万年后
2,000,000 years hence.
各种新奇的形态层出不穷
Various new forms have come into being,
每一种都有其独特的适应方式
each with its own unique adaptations
以便在这个光怪陆离的未来新地球上生存
for the strange new future Earth that they find themselves in.
其中包括“筑巢者”
These include the hiver,
他们是“社交者”的后裔，个子更高
taller descendants of the socials
因其建造巢穴和拥有蜂巢思维的状态而得名
who get their name from their hive-building and hive-mind state of being.
还有“寄生者”和“宿主”
The parasites and hosts,
这场面多少有点猎奇
a rather grotesque situation,
但对当事的双方来说似乎还挺受用
but one that seems to work for all concerned.
“旅行者”
The travellers,
“舟人”的后代
descendants of the boat people,
他们继承了先辈的游牧（游船？）生活方式
who have continued the nomadic lifestyle of their forebears.
最后
And finally,
还有“搜寻者”
the seeker,
他们是从“寻水者”演化而来的
which is descended from the water seeker.
如今“搜寻者”和“筑巢者”之间也建立了一种共生关系
A symbiotic relationship now exists between the seekers and the hivers,
“筑巢者”会利用“搜寻者”作为定位水源的“活体雷达”
who utilise the seeker as a means to locate water sources.
300万年后
3,000,000 years hence.
“树懒人”是“苔原行者”的巨型后裔，专门模仿业已灭绝的大地懒
The Slothman is a large descendant of the Tundra Dweller that imitates the now extinct Megatherium.
他们体型庞大、行动迟缓，但仍有其独特的危险之处
It is large and heavy, slow, yet still dangerous in its own way.
尽管他们是在一个没有捕食者的安逸环境中进化而来
Despite having evolved in an environment free of predators,
但大自然风云突变，意味着他们现在必须与“刺齿者”共存
shifts in nature have occurred which mean that they must now co-exist with the Spike Tooth.
这是一种酷似剑齿虎的未来人类，已经开始捕食“树懒人”
This is a Smilodon-like future human that has begun to prey on the Slothmen.
但“刺齿者”中那些没经验的“愣头青”自己
But the inexperienced among the Spike Tooths can themselves
也可能反过来沦为树懒人的盘中餐
fall prey to the Slothmen,
要是一个不留神，就会被他们庞大的身躯压成肉饼
getting crushed by their enormous bulk if they're not careful.
“食鱼者”是一种哥布林般的物种
The fish-eater is a goblin-like species
是“温带林行者”的后代
that is a descendant of the temperate woodland dweller,
“沙漠奔跑者”也是如此
as is the Desert Runner,
他们因各自环境的压力而走上了截然不同的演化道路
who have diverged greatly due to the pressures of their respective environments.
“树栖者”是“热带树栖者”的深度进化版
The Tree Dweller is an involved form of the Tropical Tree Dweller,
栖息于树上，习性也跟树懒似的
and is arboreal and sloth-like.
五百万年后
Five million years hence,
杰米兹·斯穆特和他那群太空老铁们的后裔，终于回来了
the descendants of Jimez Smoot and his space-faring brethren finally return.
然而，他们早已面目全非，看不出半点人形
However, they are completely unrecognizable as humans,
他们自己也压根没认出地球是他们的母星
and they themselves do not recognize Earth as their place of origin.
他们不觉得这是“荣归故里”
They don't see it as returning home.
只当这是又一颗资源丰富的星球，等着他们来开采和榨干
They see this world as just another resource-rich planet to mine and ring dry.
他们很快便着手基因改造地球上的生物，也就是那些未来人类的后裔
They soon set about genetically modifying the creatures of the Earth, the future human descendants,
把他们变成了各种奇形怪状的形态，供自己驱使
turning them into grotesque and freakish forms for their own use.
“工程驮兽”被培育出来，并加装了机械部件，用作运输的牲口
The engineered pack animals are bred and augmented with mechanical parts to be used as beasts of burden.
“食用生物”由“宿主”改造而来
The food creatures are made from the hosts
被设计成一坨坨肥腻的怪物，专门充当食物来源
and designed as blubbery monstrosities that serve as a food source.
而“工程工人”则由“温带林行者”创造
And the engineered workers have been created from the temperate woodland dwellers,
同样被植入了机械零件，用于承担简单的苦力活和操作机器
themselves also augmented with machine parts to undertake simple tasks and operate machinery.
最终，当地球上的一切似乎都已被榨取殆尽时
And eventually, when all had seemingly been extracted from the Earth,
这群星际人类扬长而去，去寻找新的世界加以蹂躏
the interstellar humans left to seek out new worlds to ravage.
然而，他们并没有带走地球所能给予的一切
However, they hadn't taken everything that the Earth had to offer.
在海洋的万丈深渊中，“水栖人”始终未被发现
Deep in the depths of the ocean, the aquatic has remained undetected.
作为唯一幸存的未来人类物种
The sole surviving future human species,
这些海牛般的生物似乎蓄势待发，准备有朝一日重返大洋
these manatee-like creatures seem poised to one day re-emerge from the oceans
并在未来的万古岁月中，重新殖民那片曾属于他们遥远祖先的土地
and begin to colonize the surface which belonged to their distant ancestors in the eons to come.
如果你喜欢这期关于《人后之人》的视频，并且想一探究竟
If you enjoyed this video on man after man and you want a deeper dive,
你可以去看看我的全书通读版，链接就在这里
you can check out my full reading of the book, which can be seen here.
或者，你也可以看我另一期视频，那里有对书中每个物种更详尽的解说
Or, you can watch my other video where I explain in greater detail each species found in the book.
感谢您的收看，这里是Bewarecast，我们下期视频再会
Thank you for watching. This has been the Bewarecast, and I'll catch you in the next video. Take care.